

Mario Guzmán

Career Summary

Marios is a Data Scientist, in his career he has focused on understanding business problems posed by customers. He has used different types of analytical development methodologies, such as Python, Pyspark, SQL, among others. In addition, he has worked with agile methodologies and version control.

He has more than 4 years of experience in Analytics. Mario has good skills for text analysis systems, unstructured data homologation, recommendation systems, propensity models, churn, among others. The areas in which Mario has participated are Social Media, Retail, Telecommunications, Recruiting and Teaching.

Summary of Qualifications

Proficient In:

Programming Languages

- Python
- R
- Spark
- SQL

IBM

- IBM Watson
- DB2
- IIAS
- Speech to text

Visualization

- Power BI
- Data Studio

Environment

- Docker
- Databricks

GCP

- VM
- Cloud Storage
- BigQuery
- Speech to text

AWS

- S3
- EC2
- VPC
- Sagemaker
- Athena
- EMR
- Glue
- Aws Transcribe
- Cloud 9

Versioning

- Git
- Gitlab
- Bitbucket

Languages

- Spanish (native speaker)
- English (basic speaker, intermediate reader)

Career History

Exalitica Spa., Santiago, Chile

Data Scientist

- Participation in customer purchase estimation, leakage models and upgrade models.
- Development and implementation of advanced statistical models in the area of Retail and Media.

Deloitte Chile, Santiago, Chile

Jun. 2018 – Aug. 2019

Nov. 2017 - Jun. 2018

Analyst FA

- Development of approval processes of text sources and recognition.
- Survey and development of a variable generator engine for the construction and development of analytical and business models.

Analyst Omnia AI

Mar. 2019 - Aug. 2019

- Development of different types of segmentations that describe customer behavior.
- Development of models that describe user behavior based on their heart rate, in order to define

when to include an advertisement.

Claro Chile, Santiago, Chile

Senior Data Scientist

- Generation of reports to measure analytical assets.
- Support of the company's analytical assets.
- Development of speech to text analysis, using speaker voice separation techniques, music removal and transcription to text using different types of API's available.
- Development and implementation of ideal plan recommendations for both home and mobile markets.
- Development and implementation of mobile equipment recommendation to post-paid mobile customers with leased equipment.

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso, Santiago, Chile

Aug. 2019 – to the Present

Aug. 2019 - May. 2021

- Teacher
 - Four versions delivered and in charge of its dissemination in the Predictive Modeling and Machine Learning diploma course.
 - Professor of Multivariate Methods in the Master's program in Statistics

Globant, Santiago, Chile

May. 2021 – to the Present

Semi Senior Advance Data Scientist

Project Augmented Recruiting

- Developer of improvements in audio services.
- Developer of improvements in the candidate competency estimation model.
- Product usability discovery to promote user improvements.
- Development of a model for candidates who pass the technical interview.
- Discovery of high-performing candidates.
- Profiling of globers most similar to a potential candidate.
- Development of CV Vectorization.

Relationship with universities

- Generate links with universities in order to reduce the company-university gap, particularly with the PUCV.
- Co thesis guide: Classification of E-commerce Reviews.

Education

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso, Valparaíso, Chile

Mar. 2014 - Dec. 2017

Pontificia Unviersidad Católica de Valparaíso, Valparaíso, Chile

Mar. 2019 - Jul. 2020

Master of Statistics